<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Reply to some libels lately printed against the Earl of Danby together with some observations upon Dr. Oates his narrative concerning the conspiracy of Knox, Lane, and Osborne.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57019</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12611356</idno>
  <idno type="VID">64393</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240933789</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32281</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12611356</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57019)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64393)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1534:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Reply to some libels lately printed against the Earl of Danby together with some observations upon Dr. Oates his narrative concerning the conspiracy of Knox, Lane, and Osborne.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXX [1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Leeds, Thomas Osborne, --  Duke of, 1631-1712.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64393:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64393:1"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO SOME LIBELS Lately Printed against The Earl of Danby.</p>
            <p>Together with some OBSERVATIONS UPON Dr. Oates his Narrative CONCERNING THE CONSPIRACY OF <hi>Knox. Lane,</hi> and <hi>Osborne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, M.DC.LXXX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb facs="tcp:64393:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64393:2"/>
            <head>A Reply to some Libels, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THIS is a time when the Press does without Control take so great a Liberty of defaming both King and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at their Pleasure, and the People do so easily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve whatever is in Print, (though never so false,) that it is not to be wondred to find any Subject of what quality soever exposed thereby to the most infamous Scandals and Untruth's: but when the Authours are known, they cannot expect but that they who are concern'd in such unjust Defamations, will require satisfaction at their Hands according to the Laws.</p>
            <p>Of this Sort are two late Libels against the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> and divers of his Family; One called, <hi>The Domestick Intelligence,</hi> dated <hi>Fryday</hi> the 28th. of <hi>November,</hi> 1679. Printed for <hi>Benjamin Harris</hi> at the Stationers Armes under the <hi>Royal-Exchange;</hi> And the other Intituled, <hi>The Reputation of Dr.</hi> Oates <hi>Cleared,</hi> in the Tryal of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Knox,</hi> formerly a Servant to the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> and the Lord <hi>Dumblain</hi> his Son, and Printed for <hi>Robert Harford</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1679.</p>
            <p>In the first, It is said in one place, That <hi>Thomas Knox</hi> is belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s Family; whereas he hath been dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from the said Earl's Family above 15 Moneths since. And in another place of the said Pamphlet, it is said, That on <hi>Tuesday</hi> the 25th of <hi>November</hi> last, Mr. <hi>Dangerfeild</hi> made it appear at the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> that the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> and some others of the Family were concerned in managing the whole Accusation; and that the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> was so confident of Success, that he thereupon surrendred up himself to the Usher of the <hi>Black Rod</hi> when the Parliament sat. All which is so notoriously false, that Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> did not speak one such word in Court; but on the contrary, by a Narrative of the said Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s now in Print, there is enough to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince any Impartial Reader, that what Contrivance may have been made by the <hi>Papists</hi> against any <hi>Protestant</hi> whatsoever, has
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64393:3"/>been indeavoured to be put as maliciously in Execution against the said Earl.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Benjamin Harris,</hi> I suppose he is in Fee to write Lies particularly against the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he is to send <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> every week all over the Kingdome; in which I will appeal to every Reader, whether there be one truth in Ten in that <hi>Weekly Intelligence,</hi> any more than was in his Story of a great many Pistols taken in the Earl's Chamber in the Tower, though there never came one into the House where the Earl lodgeth: And so like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise in his Pamphlet of the 9th of <hi>December</hi> last, about the Judges Opinions concerning the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> where he tells a formal story of that matter; whereas they only answered, That the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the said Earl could not legally be granted; and yet this so notorious Libel is weekly sent abroad with a Title to it of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>published to prevent false Reports.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some few dayes after the said Libel of the 28th of <hi>November,</hi> came forth that other already mentioned, under the name of clearing Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> his Reputation; but in truth doing so much the contrary, that the Doctor himself ownes it to be false; as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it has had the impudence to falsifie a Record <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Doctors Indictment against <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Lane:</hi> And that this may the better appear, I have here incerted out of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> his own Narrative, the Abstract of the said Indictment, which is in Page 2 <hi>d.</hi> as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="indictment">
                        <head>
                           <hi>Novemb.</hi> 25. 1679. Dominus Rex versus Thomam Knox &amp; Johannem Lane. <hi>For the King.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe Indictment sets forth, <hi>That whereas</hi> Edward Coleman, William Ireland, <hi>and</hi> John Groves <hi>and other false Traytors to the Jurors unknown,</hi> 24th <hi>of</hi> April <hi>in the</hi> 30th <hi>year of the King that now is, at the Parish of St.</hi> Margarets Westminster, <hi>did Trayterously Conspire, Consult and Agree amongst themselves to kill and destroy the King, and to raise War against his Majestie within this Kingdom, and to change the Religion by Law established, to the Superstition of the Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>for which Treasons, Trayterous Conspiracies, Consultations and Agreements, the said</hi> Coleman, Ireland <hi>and</hi> Groves <hi>were afterwards at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted and put to death for the same.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And whereas</hi> William <hi>Earl of</hi> Powis, William <hi>Viscount</hi> Stafford, John <hi>Lord</hi> Bellasis, Henry <hi>Lord</hi> Arundel <hi>of</hi> Wardour, William <hi>Lord</hi> Petre, <hi>and Sir</hi> Henry Tichbourn, <hi>Baronet, the</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64393:3"/>
                           <hi>last at</hi> Westminster <hi>were accused of the Treasons aforesaid, and thereupon according to due form of Law were committed to the Tower of</hi> London, <hi>to be there safely kept to answer the said Treasons whereof the said Earl of</hi> Powis <hi>and the other four Lords were by the Commons in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament assembled, Impeached.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And whereas</hi> Thomas <hi>Earl of</hi> Danby <hi>afterwards, That is to say, the</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> November <hi>last at</hi> Westminster, <hi>was in lawful manner accused of certain Treasons and other Misdemeanours, and thereupon according to due form of Law was committed to the Tower, there to be safe kept to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the Treasons and Misdemeanours aforesaid; of which said Treasons and Misdemeanours, the said Earl of</hi> Danby <hi>is Impeached by the Commons in Parliament Assembled.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And that the Defendants knowing the said Lords to be accused of the Treasons and Misdemeanours aforesaid; and the said Defendants being diabolically affected towards the King their natural Lord, and Contriving and endeavouring with all their might to disturb, hinder and stifle the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the said Treasons by the said Earl of</hi> Powis, <hi>Viscount</hi> Stafford, <hi>Lord</hi> Bellasis, Henry <hi>Lord</hi> Arundel, William <hi>Lord</hi> Petre, <hi>supposed to be Committed as aforesaid; and as much as in them lay to elude the due course of Law and retard the Prosecution of Justice against the said Five Lords, Sir</hi> Henry Tichborne, <hi>and</hi> Thomas <hi>Earl of</hi> Danby.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>They the said Defendants the</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> April <hi>last past at the Parish a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid in the County aforesaid, falsly, maliciously and unlawfully amongst themselves did consult and agree to scandalize</hi> Titus Oates, <hi>Clerk, and</hi> William Bedlow, <hi>Gent. who had given Informations of the Treasons aforesaid, and whom the said Defendants knew to have given Informations aforesaid against the Earl of</hi> Powis, <hi>Viscount</hi> Stafford, <hi>Lords</hi> Bellasis, Arundel <hi>and</hi> Petre, <hi>and to represent them upon the Tryal of the said Five Lords, to be Persons of Evil Conversation, and Witnesses not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And that the Defendant</hi> Knox <hi>afterwards, that is to say, the</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> April <hi>last at</hi> Westminster <hi>aforesaid, in the names and with the consent and agreement of the Defendant</hi> Lane, <hi>and</hi> William Osborn, <hi>to villifie the Information of the said</hi> Titus Oates, <hi>and</hi> William Bedlow, <hi>to be given for the King against the said Five Lords last mentioned; falsly, malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, subtilly and advisedly did write and cause to be written four Letters, and those Letters so written falsly</hi> &amp;c. <hi>did direct and cause to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to himself the said Defendant</hi> Knox; <hi>by which said Letters it was Falsly, Craftily and Deceitfully declared, That the said</hi> Lane <hi>and</hi> Osborn <hi>were very much troubled in their Consciences by reason of certain matters, which they well knew and did conceal concerning the unjust Contrivances
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64393:4"/>of the said</hi> Titus Oates, <hi>and</hi> William Bedlow, <hi>in accusing the said Earl of</hi> Danby <hi>to be guilty of the Treasons and other Misdemeanours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And that the said</hi> Titus Oates <hi>was a Person of a wicked and vitious Life, and did make an Assault upon the said</hi> John Lane, <hi>and did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to commit with him, the said</hi> Lane, <hi>Sodomy.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>And further, That the Defendant</hi> Knox, <hi>the sooner and more effectually to persuade the said</hi> Lane <hi>and</hi> Osborn <hi>falsly to accuse the said</hi> Titus Oates <hi>and</hi> William Bedlow, <hi>that they the said</hi> Titus Oates, <hi>and</hi> William Bedlow <hi>had unjustly, contrary to all truth, accused the said Earl of</hi> Danby <hi>of the Treasons and other Misdemeanours aforesaid, and so to affirm against the Kings Evidence upon the Tryal to be had of the said Earl of</hi> Danby <hi>for the Treasons and Misdemeanours aforesaid, afterwards the</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> April <hi>last at</hi> Westminster, <hi>falsly, advisedly, corruptly and against the Duty of his Allegiance, did give to the said</hi> Lane <hi>and</hi> Osborn <hi>divers great Sums of Money. And did promise to the said</hi> Lane <hi>and</hi> Osborn, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a certain time by the said Defendant</hi> Knox <hi>proposed, That the said</hi> Lane <hi>and</hi> Osborn <hi>should have and receive other great Sums and other Rewards for the same, to the great delay, obstruction and suppression of Justice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>Although I shall by and by say something to what concerns the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> in the said Indictment, yet my present aim in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing it, is, to shew the Egregious malice as well as falshood of the aforesaid Libel against the said Earl and his whole Family; (for almost all the Errors in falsifying the said Indictment do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern his Lordship or Family) and to prepare the Reader for his Poison, he says <hi>Knox</hi> was formerly Servant to the Earl of <hi>Danby;</hi> which he never was, but only to one of his Sons, and discharged long before any of those Contrivances are pretended. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Libeller is resolved to do his business as home as lay in his power, he would rather belie a Record, and run the hazard of any Scandal, than not venture to say, That the Indictment set forth,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>First,</hi> That the said <hi>Knox</hi> had obliged himself to introduce one <hi>Wiggens</hi> and <hi>Lane</hi> into Company with the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hour in the night Season.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Countess of <hi>Danby</hi> (who well approved of what <hi>Lane</hi> had ingaged to endeavour) did likewise offer to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the said <hi>Wiggens</hi> and his Mother to her Lord in her own Coach at any time.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That they (meaning <hi>Knox, Lane,</hi> and <hi>Osborn</hi>) deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their Information against Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> to the Lord <hi>Latimer,</hi>
                           <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64393:4"/>who kept it a few daies, <hi>and then delivered it back to be conveyed to the Lord</hi> Powis <hi>to amend.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That <hi>Knox</hi> did promise them beneficial places either in the Treasury or Customes, <hi>as from the Earl of</hi> Danby.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That they did believe that the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> only, in confidence of the Success of the design, did render himself to the Black Rod.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now, as you see, there is not one word of all this in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Indictment. So (if this Libeller may be believed in any thing) he tells you, That Mr. <hi>Thomas Willoughby,</hi> alias <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> drew the Affidavits himself out of <hi>Lanes</hi> papers: and I desire the Reader both to take notice from Mr. <hi>Dangerfield's</hi> own Narrative, whose Agent he the said Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was, as appears page 14. and to observe from what follows, what Acquaintance or Correspondence there has been at any time betwixt the Earl of <hi>Powis</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> or Lord <hi>Latimer,</hi> or any of the Family. But having laid open the great falshood of those Libels, I shall trouble you no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them at present, but leave their Authors to their due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions of the Law, which I doubt not but will meet with them.</p>
            <p>I now come to what I am sorry to find in Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> his own Narrative concerning the said Earl, because it is not suitable to his present work of defending the <hi>Protestant</hi> Interest, to endeavour the destruction of any <hi>Protestant,</hi> without great reason so to do; and in the person of the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> he ought to have been more sparing than of most men, unless he could have made out some evident demonstration of his Guilt; whereas he did never before pretend to accuse the said Earl of any thing, nor through the whole Narrative does he charge him with any one Crime, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Suppositions and Reflections, without any ground for them; I say, that without clear proof of some fault, the Doctor ought to have been more sparing of this Lord, because he knows very well how long he received protection by his care, when although Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> was not personally known to the Earl, yet himself knows, and Dr. <hi>Tong</hi> can testifie, that it was for many weeks in the Earl's power to have put an end to the Plot, and to have given both of them into the Hands of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, without appearing at all in it himself, if he would but have given the least intimation to the <hi>Papists</hi> of what they were about, and the place of their meetings, which both the said Doctors do know his Lordship was several times Privy to. It is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served also, That for a great while after the publication of Dr.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64393:5"/>
               <hi>Tong's</hi> Informations in Council, and that the Earl knew the name and had seen the person of Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> the said Doctor was so sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of these Obligations to the Earl, that instead of saying any thing to his prejudice, he gave him several good Characters; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the King and Councils Orders about money for him were short of his Expectations; and then indeed, but never till then, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to complain of the said Earl as the cause of his not being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rewarded; and since that time ha's exprest several dislikes of the said Earl; but that it may appear to be his dislike only, and nothing which could be materially objected against the Earl, I have toucht all the points in his Narrative which concerns the said Earl, and leave it to the Judgment of the Reader, whether such way of proceeding can be thought just towards any man. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> For the Indictment it self, which I have already recited out of his own Narrative, and by which there appears too much forwardness to hurt the said Earl, and to throw ill Reflections upon him, but that there was such want of matter, that it could only set forth against the Earl,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That on the 30th of <hi>November</hi> last the said Earl stood Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached in Parliament of <hi>High Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Defendants (meaning <hi>Knox, Lane</hi> and <hi>Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born</hi>) knowing the Five <hi>Popish</hi> Lords in the Tower and the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> to be accused and impeached of Treasons, and the said Defendants contriving and endeavouring to disturb, hinder and stifle the discovery of the Treasons supposed to be committed by the said Five <hi>Popish</hi> Lords, and to elude the due Course of Law, and retard the prosecution of Justice against the said Five Lords, and Sir <hi>Henry Tichborne</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Danby;</hi> did on the 30th of <hi>April</hi> last consult and agree to scandalize Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> whom the Defendants knew to have given Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Treasons against the Five <hi>Popish</hi> Lords, and with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to represent them Witnesses not to be believed upon the Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of the said Five Lords.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the Defendant <hi>Knox</hi> the 30th of <hi>April</hi> last, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Osborne</hi> to have 4 Letters written to himself, in which it was falsly <hi>&amp;c.</hi> declared, That the said <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> were troubled by reason of matters they knew and conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed concerning the contrivance of Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> of the Treasons <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That the said <hi>Knox</hi> to perswade the said <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64393:5"/>to accuse <hi>Titus Oates</hi> and <hi>William Bedlow</hi> that they had unjustly accused the said <hi>Earl,</hi> and to affirm against the Kings Evidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Tryal to be had of the said <hi>Earl for the Treasons aforesaid,</hi> did falsly <hi>&amp;c.</hi> give great Sumes of money to the said <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Osborn,</hi> and did promise the said <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Osborn,</hi> that they should have other great Sumes and other Rewards for the same.</p>
            <p>Here the Doctor doth not add (as the Pamphlet Printed for <hi>Robert Harford</hi>) the words <hi>as from the Earl of</hi> Danby; for he very well knew, that the first Letters of their Correspondence were but in <hi>April,</hi> and that the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> had quitted his Place in <hi>March</hi> before, so that he had no places in the Treasury or Customs to promise; but I wonder he should in the 4th Paragraph say these words (viz.) <hi>against the Tryal to be had of the said Earl for the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons aforesaid, when there were no Treasons at all alledged against the said Earl, either by Mr.</hi> Oares <hi>or Mr.</hi> Bedlow.</p>
            <p>Now I pray the Reader to take notice what pains has been taken to get the name of the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> crowded amongst the <hi>Popish</hi> Lords.</p>
            <p>For as to the first Paragraph, every body knew before. As to the second, it is only pretended, That on the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby's</hi> be half the Defendants designed to retard the prosecution of Justice against the Five Lords and him. In the third the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> is only named about <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Osborne's</hi> tender Consciences concerning him. And in the fourth, that <hi>Knox</hi> did give great Sums, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise other great Rewards (but say's not from whom) to make <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Osborn</hi> affirm against the King's Evidence upon the Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to be had of the Earl <hi>for the Treasons aforesaid, which I have already Remarked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All these (save the last) are so frivolous, that they need no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer; and how any of them are proved, appears not, unless the Informations of men swearing one thing to day, and another to morrow, be good evidence, which the Court ha's justly agreed them not to be; but if they were, it amounts to no more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> than things said to them by <hi>Knox,</hi> who might probably be imployed in this as well as other matters by those who Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> has proved to have released and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him; and who was never considerable enough in the <hi>Earl</hi>'s Family, to be trusted by the said Earl in any business at all. Besides that, in <hi>February</hi> before these practices, the <hi>Earl</hi> had caused him to be called before the Council, and to be severely rebuked there, for having used his Lordships name in matters of the like
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64393:6"/>nature about one <hi>Wiggens,</hi> without his Lordship's Privitie, as was then confessed by the said <hi>Knox:</hi> and I am credibly informed, that during his Abode in the said Family, he never had any admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to his Lordship, other than as any inferiour Servant in the House. But not to dwell any longer upon Circumstances, it had been necessary for the making their story good on any side, to have found first, That Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> or Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> had been Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses to be used against the <hi>Earl</hi> at his Tryal, or else how could the Affirming against their evidence signifie any thing, either to the retarding the <hi>Earl's</hi> Tryal; or the doing him prejudice at his Tryal? And consequently why should either Money or other Rewards be promised on the <hi>Earl</hi>'s behalf, for that which could not have availed him six pence, if all had been effected which those Defendants were about to prove? But I confess, it is very possible the <hi>Popish</hi> Lords might have found benefit by blasting the Kings Evidence against any body; and those who would make this <hi>Earl</hi> bear the burden of their Murders, might probably enough, find him the fittest Subject to sacrifice for any other of their purposes. But to shew that Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> nor <hi>Bedlow</hi> were not concern'd as Witnesses against this <hi>Earl,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> It is known, That the <hi>Earl</hi>'s Accusation is contained in an Impeachment of six Articles from the House of Commons, and brought up to the Lords the 23th of <hi>December</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is known likewise, That Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> have sworn both in Parliament and before the Council, that they had nothing to say against any Peer but those named in their Accusations, of whom the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> is none.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is known, That what Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> pretends to say against the said <hi>Earl,</hi> is in the <hi>February</hi> after the Impeachment of the <hi>Earl,</hi> and upon new matter; (so great a Fool must the <hi>Earl</hi> be, if that should prove true) but yet if it were so, it is not charge of Treason, not does it relate to the proving of the Charge of which the <hi>Earl</hi> stands accused in Parliament.</p>
            <p>All this I say is so well known, that I wonder every man's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory should not serve him, to vindicate the <hi>Earl</hi> from those as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persions; but I suppose the calling them to mind will be sufficient, and must also necessarily satisfie all men, that the <hi>Earl</hi>'s delivery of himself to the Black Rod, could not possibly proceed from any success he hoped or needed from what either those Defendants or any body else should prove against Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> or Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> in relation to the <hi>Earl</hi>'s Tryal, who was not accused by them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64393:6"/>
            <p> But I must needs say, I wonder yet more (and with some men it would be apt to create a hard opinion) why Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> should be the Author of so many ill Reflections on this <hi>Earl,</hi> as are scatter'd through the whole Narrative, when his safety depended so long upon the care of that Lord, that in all places abroad, and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at home, he is to this day thought to have been a contriver of the Plot with the Doctor. He says in his 3d page, That when he had informed the Reader that <hi>Knox</hi> had formerly been a Servant to one of the <hi>Earl</hi>'s Sons, he would easily suggest to himself the reason why he was so active an Instrument in this great Affair, (although he knows it could only have been to serve the <hi>Popish</hi> Lords, and do himself no good) and the Doctor himself observes at the bottom of page 4th, <hi>That if a Conspiracy could be proved against the late Lord Treasurer, it would make the Evidence against the</hi> Popish <hi>Lords vanish into smoak;</hi> in which I agree with the Doctor, That the design might be to falsifie the Testimony of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> about the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> to the end they might be of no Use against any others: but I am sure the Doctor cannot believe the following words (viz.) <hi>That the Earl's Confidence of Success made him surrender himself;</hi> because he knows (as I have said already) that he was no Witness against the <hi>Earl:</hi> Besides, the <hi>Earl</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered himself the 15th. of <hi>April,</hi> and it appears these Defendants were not with Justice <hi>Dewy</hi> till the 19th, and after that with the Secretary of State, and the Privy Council, so that on the 15th that matter was not ripe enough for any body (who had been concern'd) to promise themselves success: and who ever knows the <hi>Earl,</hi> will scarce believe of him, that if he had needed them, (as he did not) he would have relied upon the words of two infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Fellows, who were servants to the Doctor himself, and whom the <hi>Earl</hi> had never seen nor heard of before, and of whom the Doctor himself saies at the bottom of page 9th, <hi>That as it is great pitty all false accusers have not their Crimes engraven in their fore-heads with an hot Iron, so the Doctor and Capt.</hi> Bedlow <hi>must be supposed to be bereaft of their Understandings, that would contrive this villany against the Lord Treasurer, in the Hearing of a shabby Servant, who for bread came into his Service, and for better fare would quit it at a days warning. It had been equally credible, had they sworn that they had Proclaimed it by the Common Cryer.</hi> How much less credible must it therefore be, that they should be trusted by one who is a stranger to them, and when their Treachery to their own Master must alone have been sufficient to deterr any other from putting confidence in such Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64393:7"/>
            <p> The Doctor is also often pleased to call the Earl their great Patron, although he does many times quot Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> and Colonel <hi>Mansel's</hi> Proofs, of their being Agents for the <hi>Popish</hi> Lords, and they being rewarded by them, and has no other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument against the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> saving, That <hi>Knox</hi> was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a servant to one of his Sons; and he would seem to reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of the Earl's Sons, because <hi>Knox</hi> made Use of his name to a Justice of Peace; which is probably not true, because the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice declared in Court, he was not known to him; but if it had been so, I think the fault had been on the other side, if a Son hearing any thing which concern'd the Life of his Father, had not endeavoured by all waies and means to get the truth disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
            <p>These things, I must confess, to me do not seem suitable to the Doctor's other good services, nor to the Introduction of his own Narrative, nor to the profession of a Divine, who (as he saies of himself, page the 9th.) <hi>who ever knowes must confess him a Person, who has learnt the moderation of the Tongue to that exactness, that he could not possibly be guilty of such Extravagances as are said against him.</hi> And in the Introduction, page the 3d. he calls it a <hi>Cursed Design</hi> to in validate his Testimony and Mr. <hi>Bedlow's,</hi> by fixing upon them a Conspiracy against the Life of the Earl of <hi>Danby;</hi> and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the same page, he justly accuses those men of prostituted Consciences, who attempt the Murder of his good name; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not therefore but hope from that good and pious Rule, that the Doctor intends not those Reflections so ill against the Earl, as they are generally understood (unless, as I have said before) he had had some demonstration of a Crime to be objected against the said Earl; whereas nothing does appear through the whole Narrative, but what arises out of <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Osborn</hi>'s Informations, who have been so many times forsworn, and which at best would have been but Hear-sayes from <hi>Knox,</hi> whom Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> shews to have been one of the <hi>Popish</hi> Agents at the same time with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; out of whose Narrative I will refresh your Memory with some passages which relate to this matter.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of it, Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> relates his being taken out of Prison, and employed by the <hi>Papists</hi> only; and in page the 7th he tells you, That they gave him Money to compound his Debts, which were near 700 <hi>l.</hi> (so considerable an Agent Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> was designed to be for them;) and one of the first Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices which he was to be employ'd in, was, to destroy at least the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64393:7"/>reputation if not the Life of the Earl of <hi>Danby;</hi> by being put to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perse the <hi>Danby-Reflections,</hi> written by <hi>Nevile,</hi> at the same time when the said <hi>Nevile</hi> sent him the Letter about giving <hi>Opium</hi> to <hi>Stroud;</hi> and the Countess of <hi>Powis</hi> used to send for the said Reflections as they were transcribing; and once sent him 5 Guinneys to incourage him, as appears page the 5th.</p>
            <p>In the 8th page the said Countess tells him, he was yet but upon small business, but there were other Affairs cut out for him, which appears, by the following discourse, to be,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Endeavours to kill the King, or at least the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To lay the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmund-bury Godfrey</hi> to the Earl of <hi>Danby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And to lay the Plot to the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of these Designs, they begin with Charging the said Murder on the said Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> as appeares in the pages 16 and 17.</p>
            <p>By the 11th page, It appears, that <hi>Nevile</hi> was a principal man, both for his Pen and his Advice, in giving Instructions; and we find that Pen as bitterly employ'd against the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby,</hi> as any other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom their Contrivances were designed.</p>
            <p>In the pages 12, 13, 14, 15. is the History of the Contrivances about Dr. <hi>Oates;</hi> which pages I have caused to be Printed and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, because it will thereby clearly appear,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> That the <hi>Papists</hi> were the sole managers of that whole busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness against the Doctor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That <hi>Lane</hi> in his first Letter (page 13) writes, That he will do the <hi>Catholicks</hi> the greatest service imaginable, by discovering what he knowes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> released <hi>Lane.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Nevile</hi> (the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi>'s good Friend) released <hi>Knox,</hi> who (notwithstanding) must now be thought the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi>'s Agent (so ill doe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes of the <hi>Earl's</hi> Enemies agree with their malice.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That <hi>Knox,</hi> when released, came to <hi>Powis</hi>-House; where by the said Countesses Order, he treated with Mrs. <hi>Celliers</hi> about Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Oates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That his Papers were delivered to Mr. <hi>Dangerfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> That <hi>Dangerfield</hi> sent them to the Tower (and by the way, amongst Mr. <hi>Dangerfields</hi> many Journeys to the Tower, none of them was ever to the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> That he drew an Affidavit for <hi>Lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> That the Indictment against <hi>Oates</hi> was Penn'd by the Lord <hi>Castlemain,</hi> and <hi>Nevile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> That <hi>Knox</hi> not being in a Condition to defend his Tryal
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64393:8"/>(having often desired to borrow money of Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi>) the said Countess promised him Money; and if he should want at any time, Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> should furnish him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> That Lord <hi>Powis</hi> sent <hi>Lane</hi> out of the way into <hi>Essex,</hi> and took Care for their Lodgings.</p>
            <p>In the pages 68 and 69 appears <hi>Nevil's</hi> own Confession, That the <hi>Danby</hi>-Reflections pass'd by his Hands:</p>
            <p>That he gave his Advice upon the Papers of <hi>Knox, Lane</hi> and <hi>Os<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born;</hi> and he acknowledges,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he had twenty times advised the Indicting</hi> Oates <hi>and</hi> Bedlow.</p>
            <p>Now as all these are matters of Fact (if Mr. <hi>Dangerfield's</hi> Evidence be good) so I think this alone would be sufficient to clear the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby,</hi> or any of his Family, from those base foregoing aspersions which are thrown upon them.</p>
            <p>By a Clause in page 23 they seem to joyn the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> with the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> for the Murder of Sir <hi>Edmundb. Godfrey,</hi> where the Lord <hi>Powis</hi> (speaking how easily his man <hi>Wood</hi> might have killed Lord <hi>Shaftsbury</hi>) says, <hi>If we were rid of him (as they were of Sir</hi> Edmundb. Godfrey) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which they must certainly intend the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> to be understood for one, as by the same Lord or Lady, or both, the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> has been named for another; and to say truth, the only difference of their usage betwixt the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> and <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> has been, that they would have Murdered the first by a dagger, and the latter by a pretence of Justice, together with the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Murder of his good Name.</p>
            <p>Although what has been said, cannot but be sufficient to satisfie all reasonable men of the falshood of the foregoing Aspersions; yet to such a degree is the malice of some men raised against the said <hi>Earl,</hi> and all untruths of that kind are so readily believed, that it may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be necessary to let it be known, That the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> nor his Son <hi>Latimer,</hi> who ought to have great intimacy with the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Powis</hi> (if some of the foregoing Reflections were true) have scarce any acquaintance with the said <hi>Earl,</hi> saving that the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> hath sometimes had occasion of sending to the said <hi>Earl</hi> for Rent due to him; but I have great reason to believe them to be so much stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to one another, that although both of them have been divers Months Prisoners in the Tower, I am satisfied by enquiry, there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pass'd one Visit betwixt them, nor do I believe they have ever spoke to one another in the whole time of their Imprisonments; and truly by what is informed by Mr. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> and in a manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest by Mr. <hi>Nevile,</hi> the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> hath as little Obligation to the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Powis,</hi> as he hath Acquaintance with him.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64393:8"/>
            <p> I fear he is not much more beholding to any of that Religion; nor can I imagine why they should be thought to mean better to the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby,</hi> than to those on whom they would have laid the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plot; when the same hand (viz. <hi>Nevile</hi>) was the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of framing the contrivances against both, and to the destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both, if their Designs could have taken effect: for in page the 10th Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi> tells you, That the Method and Management of the Plot against the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> was to be Trusted only to the 5 Lords in the Tower, and Mr. <hi>Nevile;</hi> so that the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby</hi> was to be intrusted in nothing, but the prosecution of Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> which (as I have already made appear) concern'd none but those Lords.</p>
            <p>By all this you may see what a man their Malice hath found of this <hi>Earl,</hi> to make a Partner with those, who are not only seeking his Ruine by all the wayes they can invent, but from whom the said <hi>Earl</hi> is separated by the greatest difference both of Principles and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that is possible.</p>
            <p>And as it is apparent, that those base Slanders, of the <hi>Earl</hi>'s being privy to the Murder of Sir <hi>Edmundb. Godfrey,</hi> and being an inventor of the Plot <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doe come from the Papists against him; so I do from my Soul believe, a great cause of his Persecution and Restraint pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from them. Nay so inveterate are they against him, that some will father the Lord <hi>Stafford's</hi> knowledge of the late Prorogation (before it was declared in Council) to come from the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Danby's</hi> Telling it to the Lord <hi>Stafford;</hi> and yet I have heard the said <hi>Earl</hi> had not then stirr'd out of his Chamber, by reason of sickness, in 11 or 12 weeks; and, I am confident, had not seen the Lord <hi>Stafford</hi> in some time before.</p>
            <p>Nor have I ever heard that the <hi>Earl</hi> hath given any Visits, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieved any from any of the <hi>Popish</hi> Lords in the <hi>Tower</hi> ever since his Confinement.</p>
            <p>Having read and heard these foregoing false Stories, and many such Invectives against this <hi>Earl,</hi> I thought my self bound in consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to inform the World of them; that by comparing things which are Publick (as I have done) they may convince themselves of the great Injuries done every day to this Lord, and thereby judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all who profess themselves good <hi>Protestants,</hi> ought not rather to commiserate this Lord's Unjust sufferings, than have any Share in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Misfortunes.</p>
            <div type="narrative">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64393:9"/>
               <head>Here follow the Pages <hi>12, 13, 14, &amp; 15.</hi> of Mr. <hi>Dangerfield's</hi> Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative in his own words, which are refer'd to, in Page <hi>7, 12, 13, 14.</hi> of this Discourse. Viz.</head>
               <p>Lord <hi>Powis</hi> asked me whether I had a faculty of Writing abusive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and like a Satyrist, and was Master of such a Style as would look well in Print? for, said his Lordship, that Sot <hi>Nevil</hi> is so very dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, it is not to be endured; therefore if you dare undertake the Writing of some sound Pamphlets, it might be of very great Use to us. To which I replied, <hi>That I was not a Competent Judge of my own abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, but would do my best.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then Lord <hi>Powis</hi> told me, Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> should be allowed Ten shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings <hi>per</hi> Week to Dyet me, and his Lorship would allow me Three pound <hi>per</hi> Week for my expences in Business; and what ever hapned to be beyond that, I should put into a Bill, and bring or send it to his Lordship, and I should forthwith have it paid; the said Three pound ten shillings <hi>per</hi> Week was constantly paid me, whilst I serv'd them.</p>
               <p>Then I was advised by both the Lords to lodge at <hi>Powis-House,</hi> which advice came very seasonably; for I knew very well, that I had given my Landlord just occasion to harbour strange thoughts of me, and conceive suspitions to my disadvantage.</p>
               <p>About the Eighteenth of <hi>June,</hi> the Countess, who knew that I was then lodged in <hi>Powis-House,</hi> and by her Lord's order, sent me with a Letter to the Lady <hi>Tukes</hi> Lodgings in <hi>Scotland-Yard;</hi> which Lady seemed to take particular notice of me, and was pleased to say she liked me very well, and gave me two Guineys, and demanded if I durst undertake a desperate Enterprise? I answered <hi>Yes;</hi> then she went into her Closet, and wrote a Letter for the Countess of <hi>Powis,</hi> and gave it me to carry her, and so I took my leave.</p>
               <p>In my Return, I went to wait on my Lord <hi>Castlemain,</hi> who asked where I had been? I answer'd, at the Lady <hi>Tukes,</hi> and so told his Lordship how she received me; at which he seemed to be well-pleased, and smiled, and demanded if the Countess of <hi>Powis</hi> had not delivered to me, her self, or caused to be deliver'd some Papers rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to a business of <hi>Oates,</hi> for which one <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Lane</hi> were in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the <hi>Gate-House.</hi> To which I answer'd <hi>No.</hi> Then said he, I will write to the Countess about it, and order you Money, and give you directions how to proceed in it. There I waited till his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship writ a Letter, which I carried to Lady <hi>Powis;</hi> but first being sent for up, I gave her Ladyship the Letter, who, before she opened it, told me, Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> would give me Money to get <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Lane</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:64393:9"/>out of Prison. I then asked what they were in Custody for? The Lady modestly answered, 'twas by <hi>Oates</hi>'s means; but if I could get them out, he should not reign long in his Roguery. From thenceforth I undertook it, and had all the business, and Papers delivered me, by one <hi>Lawson</hi> an Attorney of <hi>Clement's-Inn,</hi> who had been endeavouring two Terms to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them by <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> but could not: I forthwith went to the <hi>Gate-house,</hi> and found means to supply them both with Money, though they were close confin'd; and, by a course that I took upon advice with the Priests, there they had Pen, Ink, and Paper conveyed to them both, but especially <hi>Lane,</hi> who writ the first Letter, which was to this effect,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will die, before I will comply with that Villain</hi> Oates,
<note place="margin">Note.</note>
                  <hi>and if any good People will work my Liberty, I will do</hi> the Catholicks <hi>the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Service imaginable, by Discovering what I know of</hi> Oates; <hi>This is from the bottom of my heart, and what I will die with,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So help me God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Letter was taken from <hi>Lane</hi>'s hand under the door, by one <hi>Tempest,</hi> then a Prisoner in the <hi>Gate-House;</hi> and by him gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to one Mrs. <hi>Ayry,</hi> who brought it to me at <hi>Powis-House,</hi> and I shewed it the Countess, who was more transported with joy than I can express; and breaking out as it were into a Rapture, <hi>Has God given us this unexpected help,</hi> said she? <hi>Well, we will (God willing) employ it to the best advantage;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> charging me to use all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition to get them both out; and then I withdrew. But as I understood the next day, the good Countess, was the greater part of that day on her knees, to render Thanks to Almighty God, for this new occasion of strength, that she supposed he had been pleased to bless their Cause with.</p>
               <p>From that time <hi>I was very industrious in this business;</hi> and had several Motions in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> before I could get either of them to the <hi>Bar; but at last I brought</hi> Lane <hi>out upon Bail, to the great Satisfaction of the whole</hi> Catholick <hi>Party,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> but <hi>Knox</hi> I could not get out; but have since been inform'd by himself, <hi>That</hi> Nevel <hi>told some Friends of his, that he did it; and had Money from the Lords in the</hi> Tower <hi>for that purpose.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now when I had got <hi>Lane</hi> out, the Countess ordered me to bring him to <hi>Powis-House;</hi> and lodge him there for the present, and she would allow Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> Ten shillings <hi>per</hi> Week for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64393:10"/>His Dyet also, as she did for mine; then came Mr. <hi>Wood,</hi> the Countesses Gentleman, one day, and said his Lord had ordered that <hi>Lane</hi> should go by the name of <hi>Johnson,</hi> as he did afterwards, during the time he continued there, which was about three Weeks; and Lady <hi>Powis</hi> in my Hearing gave order to the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he should bid the rest of the Servants take care that Mr. <hi>Johnson</hi> went not abroad, for they were in a thousand fears and Jealousies concerning him.</p>
               <p>First, lest Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> should find him, and clap him again in Prison.</p>
               <p>Secondly, lest he should run away of his own accord to Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and be prevail'd with to give some Testimony against the Lords. And</p>
               <p>Thirdly, lest the whole Design of this Plot should miscarry thereby; for they thought it concerned them as much, to inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate the King's Evidence, and render the persons of his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses infamous; as to act any other part whatsoever.</p>
               <p>At the same time that Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> gave order for the altering of <hi>Lane</hi>'s name, I gave him a Bill of <hi>Lane</hi>'s Charges to carry to the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> which amounted to near Twenty pound; about Fourteen days after, the Lords had other occasions for raising a contribution, and amongst other Money, this was then collected, and paid to Mrs. <hi>Cellier;</hi> for she had furnished me with Money for <hi>Lane,</hi> as she did for my own business, to the value of near One hundred pound; and that very night that <hi>Wood</hi> paid Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi> the twenty pound (for that was the Sum he brought) he smiled on me; and told me, it would not be long e're the worst was finished; For, said he, the Lords have consulted, that before <hi>Oates</hi> is indicted, there must a Rumour be spread abroad of a Plot amongst the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> and something of it must be made appear, to beget a belief in the People of it; them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of it, he told me, or at least a great part of it, would be for me in a little time.</p>
               <p>But after <hi>Lane</hi> came from the <hi>Gate-House,</hi> and before <hi>Knox</hi> could get out, one Mrs. <hi>Ayry,</hi> who went to <hi>Lane</hi> before, went then to <hi>Knox,</hi> or rather to the Priests; for they were so close confin'd, that 'twas very difficult, and dangerous to speak with either of them themselves; but some of the Priests there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed Pen, Ink, and Paper to him under the door, with which he also wrote; and as he has told me since, he had that conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of writing the Papers against Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> which, he said, were all Pen'd by himself.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:64393:10"/>
               <p> Now when <hi>Knox</hi> was released out of Prison, he came also to <hi>Powis-House</hi> by the direction of Mrs. <hi>Ayry, where by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesses order he treated with Mrs.</hi> Cellier <hi>about the Indicting of</hi> Oates;
<note place="margin">Note.</note>
                  <hi>and</hi> Knox <hi>did by Mrs.</hi> Celliers <hi>Request enter into a correspondence with me;</hi> and a while after <hi>deliver'd me the Papers</hi> which <hi>Lane</hi> and <hi>Osborn</hi> had given the said <hi>Knox</hi> at first, before either of them were committed: <hi>Those Papers I sent to the Tower,</hi> from thence they were sent to <hi>Nevel</hi> in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> who made <hi>what alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in them, he thought fit;</hi> and sent a Letter to me by Mrs. <hi>Cellier</hi>'s Boy (who used to carry Letters between his Mistress and me, and <hi>Nevil,</hi> and the <hi>Tower,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>with directions to draw up an</hi> Affidavit <hi>for</hi> Lane <hi>to Swear</hi> (which I did accordingly) before Sir <hi>James Butler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A little after this, Nevil <hi>sent</hi> Knox <hi>his Papers to Lord</hi> Castle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main to peruse, and make what additions or alterations his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship should think fit. He sent them to Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note>
                  <hi>who gave them me to deliver to</hi> Knox, <hi>which I did;</hi> and he has since out of those Papers, drawn an <hi>Affidavit,</hi> and persuaded one <hi>Osborn,</hi> lately a Servant to Mr. <hi>Oates,</hi> to swear the same before Sir <hi>William Dolbin</hi> Knight; and these are the Papers, out of which an Indictment was to be framed against Mr. <hi>Oates;</hi> the Contents of the said Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per I cannot remember, farther than the bare matter of Fact, which was,</p>
               <p>That Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> was to be Indicted, first for <hi>Perjury;</hi> and if he were not Convicted upon that, then a second Indictment was to be preferr'd against him for a <hi>Buggery</hi> pretended to have been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted on the person of <hi>John Lane,</hi> who I suppose now offers to Swear the same:
<note place="margin">Note.</note>
                  <hi>though the Indictment was drawn by the most veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Pens of Lord</hi> Castlemain, <hi>and his true Second,</hi> Nevel; and what he should Swear, was by them, and others put into his Mouth.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Knox</hi> had prevail'd with <hi>Osborn</hi> to Swear the said <hi>Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit,</hi> he came to shew it me, and offered to let me take a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; but I being employed in other Affairs of greater importance, had not then time to Transcribe it, only I told the Countess what <hi>Knox</hi> had done, who was very glad of it; and then believed what I said to be truth (though now her Ladyships opinion of me is much alter'd) <hi>and the Countess at the same time asked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note>
                  <hi>if</hi> Knox <hi>were in a Condition to defend his Tryal. I told her I supposed not, for that he had divers times desired me to lend him Money;</hi> Then the Countess promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed he should have Money; and bid me tell him so, to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him, (which I did) and the Countesses farther Command
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64393:11"/>was, that if <hi>Knox</hi> did at any time want Money, I should furnish him, and place it to account; and that all the Money, which should be Collected for him should pass through my name, and as Money lent him by me, lest any thing should be discover'd.</p>
               <p>About the Fourteenth of <hi>July,</hi> I went to the <hi>Tower;</hi> for their Lordships had sent for me, where I received orders to have <hi>Lane</hi> sent out of the way from <hi>Powis-house;</hi> for, <hi>said the Lord</hi> Powis, I am informed that <hi>Oates</hi> is making enquiry after him, which if it be true, and he should be found at my house, 'twould ruine us all; but I being employed in other business could not send him away immediately, according to his Lordships Order.</p>
               <p>About a day or two after, the Countess, amongst other things, earnestly desired me to send <hi>Lane</hi> into the Countrey; for, said she, <hi>Oates</hi> is bustling about after him. The next day Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> brought me Money, which I gave to <hi>Lane,</hi> and such necessaries as he had occasion for, and I sent him down to <hi>Greys</hi> in <hi>Essex;</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to send him ten shillings every week (for that was his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant allowance.) Soon after, he sent me word, that <hi>Oates</hi> had by some means or other heard where he was; and therefore he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired to be removed to some other place; then by the Countes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses order I took horse, and went to him, and sent him to Town again to <hi>Powis-house,</hi> where he continued two or three days longer.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:64393:11"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>